Finding Aid for McDonald Family Papers 1783-1938
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
McDonald Family Papers 1783-1938
McDonald family.
1 oversize volumes
2 oversize folders
2.4 linear feet
Detroit family; one member, James Henry McDonald, was a graduate of the University of Michigan (B.A., 1876; Law, 1878), who practiced law in Detroit; his wife, Christine Jewell, was active in the state Democratic Party. The collection has been arranged into five series: the McDonald Family, the Martha Wells McLellan Family, the Christine Jewell Family, Miscellaneous Files, and Photographs.
0235 Aa 2 Ac AC UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Materials were received in February 2001 from Ketura Thunder-Haab, current owner of the James McDonald estate in Glencoe Hills, Ypsilanti. (Donor no. 9064 )
The collection is open for research.
The McDonald / McLellan / Jewell family collection relates primarily to the activities of James Henry McDonald, his second wife Martha Wells McLellan and her family, and his third wife Christine Jewell and her family.
James Henry McDonald (1853-1934) was a Detroit lawyer. He was educated at the University of Michigan, receiving his B.A. from the Department of Literature, Science & the Arts in 1876 and his LL.B. from the Law Department in 1878. Throughout his life, he remained involved with University events and helping to coordinate his class reunions.
James McDonald was married three times. His first wife, Martha Ireton, died suddenly in 1889. They had one daughter together, Martha Ireton McDonald. James later married Martha Wells McLellan. Together they had three daughters, Mary McLellan McDonald (Harris), Elizabeth Ann McDonald (Smith), and Margaret McDonald (Parr). Martha McLellan passed away in 1900 leaving extensive land holdings in Detroit, particularly along Cass Avenue and Woodward Avenue. The distribution of these lands among the children became a long-standing debate in the family.
Christine Jewell became James's third wife. Christine was an active Democrat and increasingly became involved with politics. She worked her way through the party to the position of vice chairman of the Democratic State Central Committee in 1937. She spent a large portion of time in Washington, D.C. and became well known among political figures. She was also heavily involved in the Daughters of the American Revolution and held various positions within the organization. She was also an avid genealogist, compiling histories and collecting materials about the Jewell family, the McDonalds, and the families of McDonald's other wives.
Christine's father was William Franklin Jewell, a successful Detroit businessman. After working in other faculty positions around the city, he founded the Detroit Business University in 1864. As president, he became a highly esteemed professional. He was involved with many Detroit activities including the Banker's Club, the Municipal League of Detroit, and was a member of the Church of Our Father, Universalist.
James McDonald retired in 1928. He and Christine moved to their country estate, Glencoe Hills, in Ypsilanti. He passed away in 1934.
The McDonald papers contain personal and business papers collected by James Henry McDonald and by his wife Christine Jewell McDonald. The collection includes correspondence, ledgers, genealogical material and family histories, business records and photographs. Topics and activities documented in the collection include James McDonald's education at the University of Michigan and law practice in Detroit; genealogy of the McDonald, Hallock, McLellan and Jewell families; business papers of William Jewell, including some relating to his founding of the Detroit Business University in 1864; correspondence of Emma Jewell's life as a Christian Scientist; Ogden Jewell's experience as a University of Michigan Student and his enlistment in the Spanish-American War; and correspondence of Christie Jewell concerning her activities in the Democratic party, including a term a vice-chair of the state Democratic Party Central Committee in 1937-1938.
The collection contains five series: McDonald Family, the Martha Wells McLellan Family, Christine Jewell Family, Miscellaneous Files, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Christian Scientists--Michigan.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Detroit Business University.; Jewell family.; McDonald family.; McDonald, James Henry, 1853-1934.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Spanish-American War, 1898.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; Women in politics--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Algonac (Mich.); Business enterprises--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit Business University.; Jewell family.; McDonald family.; McDonald, James Henry, 1853-1934.; Residences--Michigan--Ypsilanti.
Contributors:
Jewell, Ogden.; Jewell, William Franklin.; McDonald, Christine Jewell.; McDonald, James Henry, 1853-1934.; McLellan, Martha Wells.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- McDonald Family
  The McDonald Family series includes ledgers, correspondence and other papers of James McDonald's ancestors. This series also includes personal and professional papers of James McDonald regarding his studies at the University of Michigan and his relationship with family members. The McDonald Family series contains two subseries: Early and Miscellaneous papers and James McDonald's papers.
  - Early and Miscellaneous
    The Early and Miscellaneous papers include ledgers, correspondence, and land deeds from James McDonald's grandparents and great-grandparents. Included is William McDonald's ledger documenting his work as the treasurer for Mt. Clemens from 1840 to 1848. This series also includes a family history compiled by Christine Jewell McDonald in the early 1900s.
    - Family History, 18th and 19th Century (Box 1)
    - Land Deeds (Detroit, Macomb County, and New York State) 1810-1847 (Folder Ac)
    - Ledgers
      - Cash Book (probably owned by Richard McDonald) 1783-1837 (Folder AC)
      - Personal and Business 1809-1850 (Box 1)
      - Mt. Clemens, Macomb Township 1840-1848 (Box 1)
    - Poetry and Writings undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1864-1886 (Box 1)
  - James McDonald
    The second subseries within the McDonald Family is the papers of James McDonald. This subseries documents McDonald's personal and professional life. McDonald's career in law is not documented in his papers aside from a few files regarding the founding and development of the St. John's Episcopal Church in Detroit and in Royal Oak. However, traces of his professional life are revealed in his personal correspondence with his children. He handled the business affairs of his children, often fueling stormy relations within the family. These letters detail the widening of Woodward Avenue in Detroit, and land holdings along Cass Avenue in Detroit and Geddes Road in Ann Arbor. McDonald's correspondence reveals his financial decline during the Depression. McDonald's daughters also attended the University of Michigan and describe life from the Sorosis House and the Newberry Residence. A small folder of material regarding McDonald's first wife, Martha Ireton McDonald, is also included.
    - University of Michigan
      - Literary Class of 1876 1876-1932 (Box 1)
      - Law Class of 1878 1927-1929 (Box 1)
    - Business Credentials 1869-1877 (Box 1)
    - Law Activities 1880-1931 (Box 1)
    - Estate of Martha Ireton McDonald 1889-1899 (Box 1)
    - Desk Book 1927 (Box 1)
    - St. John's Episcopal Church, Royal Oak
      - 1914-1926 (Box 1)
      - 1927-1930 (Box 1)
        (see also Ac folder)
    - St. John's Episcopal Church, Detroit 1921-1928 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Personal 1883-1919 (Box 1)
      - Martha McDonald 1909-1912 (Box 1)
      - Mary McDonald Harris and Wilmer Harris 1913-1933 (Box 1)
      - Elizabeth McDonald Smith and Clark Smith
        - 1920-1925 (Box 1)
        - 1926-1928 (Box 1)
      - Margaret McDonald Parr and MacGregor Armstrong Parr
        - 1911-1924 (Box 1)
        - 1925-1933 (Box 1)
- Martha Wells McLellan Family
  The Martha Wells McLellan Family series includes family and business papers from members of the family of McDonald's second wife. The series is divided into two subseries: Hallock family and McLellan Family.
  - Hallock Family
    The Hallock Family subseries contains an assortment of collected genealogical materials and land deeds from Washtenaw County, Genesee County, and Detroit.
    - Family History 1834-1928 (Box 1)
    - Land Deeds (Washtenaw County, Genesee County, Detroit) 1836 (Folder Ac)
  - McLellan Family
    The McLellan Family subseries also includes genealogical material as well as correspondence between Andrew McLellan, John C. McLellan, and other family members. These detail land holdings, business affairs, and deaths in the family.
    - History and Wills 1869-1902 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Andrew McLellan 1859-1894 (Box 1)
      - John C. McLellan 1869-1878 (Box 1)
- Christine Jewell Family
  The Christine Jewell family papers includes some papers of William Franklin Jewell, founder of Detroit Business University, papers of Emma Jewell detail her life as Christian Scientist, letters of Ogden Jewell relate to his studies at the University of Michigan and Spanish American War enlistment. Christine Jewell's papers concern Democratic party affairs, 1937-1938. The collection also includes miscellaneous non-family papers, and photographs. The Christine Jewell Family series contains two subseries, Early and Miscellaneous and Correspondence of family members
  - Early and Miscellaneous
    Early and Miscellaneous contains family obituaries and a current topic essay book from Richmond Public School in Wisconsin. Also in this subseries are the business papers of William Franklin Jewell relating in part to the founding of the Detroit Business University.
    - Obituaries 1877-1911 (Box 1)
    - Richmond Public School Essays (Wisconsin) 1860 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Business University 1864-1912 (Box 1)
    - William F. Jewell Business Papers 1856-1911 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence subseries contains letters from different family members. Isaac and S. Jewell describe farm life and family events. Margaret and William Jewell's correspondence is also about their family life. Emma Jewell details her personal life as a Christian Scientist. She also describes the declining mental status and asylum life of her sister, Mary. Ogden Jewell's letters are particularly rich with detail. His correspondence detail his University of Michigan student days, his search for engineering work in the western United States, and his enlistment in the Spanish American War. There is also a folder devoted to sympathy letters received after the deaths of William and Margaret's daughters, Emma and Margaret.
    - S. Jewell and Isaac Jewell 1866-1912 (Box 1)
    - Margaret B. Jewell and William Franklin Jewell
      - 1868-1891 (Box 1)
      - 1892-1911 (Box 1)
    - Emma Jewell
      - 1869-1874 (Box 1)
      - 1881-1889 (Box 2)
      - 1890-1891 (Box 2)
      - 1892-1893 (Box 2)
      - 1894-1896 (Box 2)
      - 1897-1898 (Box 2)
      - 1899-1900 (Box 2)
      - 1901 (Box 2)
      - 1902-1903 (Box 2)
      - 1904-1908 (Box 2)
    - Mary McDonald Ogden and George Ogden 1868-1897 (Box 2)
    - Orecia Ogden 1868-1894 (Box 2)
    - Ogden Jewell
      - 1892-1893 (Box 2)
      - 1894-1896 (Box 2)
      - 1897 (Box 2)
      - 1898 (Box 2)
      - 1899 (Box 2)
      - 1900-1902 (Box 2)
      - 1903 (Box 2)
      - 1904 (Box 2)
      - 1905 (Box 2)
    - Franklin Jewell 1903-1904 (Box 2)
    - Regarding Margaret B. Jewell and William Franklin Jewell's Children's Deaths 1886-1906 (Box 2)
    - Christine Jewell McDonald
      Christine Jewell's correspondence follows her political activities within the state Democratic party. They are mainly letters to fellow political figures although there are a to few constituents as well. These files are in her original alphabetical filing scheme. The library did not receive files from the latter portion of the alphabet.
      - Family 1904-1933 (Box 2)
      - Daughters of the American Revolution 1914-1919 (Box 2)
      - Political 1937-1938
        - A-B (Box 2)
        - Andrew Belanger (Secretary, Democratic State Central Committee) (Box 2)
        - C-D (Box 2)
        - Mary Dewson (Vice Chairman, Democratic National Committee) (Box 2)
        - E-F (Box 2)
        - James A. Farley (Postmaster General) (Box 2)
        - G-H (Box 2)
        - Norman Hill (Executive Secretary, Executive Office, Michigan) (Includes Glencoe Hills Estate Description) (Box 2)
        - I-K (Box 2)
        - L-M (Box 2)
        - Dorothy McAllister (Director, Women's Division, Democratic National Committee)
          - 1937 (Box 2)
          - 1938 (Box 2)
        - Michigan Democratic Women by County (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
        - Frank Murphy (Governor, Michigan) (Box 3)
        - N-O (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Files
  Miscellaneous Files are ones that could not be associated with any particular family. One folder details the service and death of Lieutenant Edward B. Gibson in World War I. Another contains old recipes, mainly for wine. There is also a treaty for the Village of Pleasant Ridge in this series. The last folder contains papers of a German immigrant and resident of Royal Oak, John Henry Weber. He was a landscaper and also sold nursery items. His papers were found in a separate shoebox.
  - Lt. Edward B. Gibson 1919 (Box 3)
  - Recipes (Box 3)
  - Village of Pleasant Ridge Treaty 1915-1918 (Box 3)
  - John Henry Weber 1904-1929 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The last series contains Photographs of the McDonald and Jewell families. These include general snapshots, formal portraits, and the family home in Ypsilanti. There are also photos of the Detroit Business University and its faculty.
  - McDonald Family
    - General (Box 3)
    - Estate, Glencoe Hills, Ypsilanti (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook, Family Vacation to Colorado 1911 (Box 3)
  - Jewell Family
    - Portraits (Box 3)
    - Houses (Box 3)
      (see also outsized folder UAm)
    - Family Cottage, Pointe du Chene (Algonac) (Box 3)
    - Detroit Business University (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Portraits (Box 3)
Related Material
In 2011, the library received additional James Henry McDonald papers within the Sarah Drake Smith Fors collection.